Finding Aid for the S.A. Griffin collection of underground poetry, Scott Wannberg, and The Carma Bums LSC.2248
UCLA Library Special Collections
S.A. Griffin collection of underground poetry, Scott Wannberg, and The Carma Bums
circa 1950-2015
UCLA Library Special Collections
Griffin, S. A.
Perrotta, Lorraine M.
LSC.2248
189.2 linear feet (276 document boxes, 5 half document boxes, 6 record storage cartons, 12 flat boxes, 19 oversize flat boxes, 9 scrapbook boxes, 5 tubes, and 15 other disparate oversize items)
4.5 linear feet (4 unprocessed boxes)
S.A. Griffin is a poet, performance artist, publisher, and actor with deep roots in the Los Angeles poetry and punk scenes beginning in the 1980s. The collection contains monographs, serials, manuscripts, correspondence, ephemera, audiovisual material, artwork, and memorabilia reflective of Griffin's extensive connections to Los Angeles poets and performance, including the Venice West Beat scene. The collection also includes the papers of fellow poet Scott Wannberg.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital and audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Accruals
The 2016 additions include monographs and serials by Griffin and collected by Griffin. These can be found in boxes 331 to 345. The additions also include materials that were interfiled in the following series and subseries: correspondence, subject files (chiefly photographs), performance files (chiefly photographs), art (photographs and collages by Tony Scibella, Justice Howard, and Dennis Olanzo Callwood), writings about Griffin (a clipping), acting files (photographs), and memorabilia (chiefly photographs and a DVD).
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Partial purchase and gift of S.A. Griffin and Lorraine Perrotta, 2014. Additions from Griffin and Perrotta, 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9977147553606533
Biography/History
S.A. Griffin (Steven Allan Griffin), born March 16, 1954, is a poet, performance artist, publisher, and actor. After graduating from high school in 1972, Griffin voluntarily entered the United States Air Force as an administration specialist and was honorably discharged in 1976. In 1978, Griffin relocated to Los Angeles from San Francisco with a scholarship to attend the Los Angeles Civic Light Opera Workshop. Griffin's awards for his work on stage and on camera include a Dramalogue Award and a Kari Award.
In 1982, Griffin became involved with poetry when he began attending open poetry readings at the Water Espresso Gallery in Hollywood. During this time he became active in the punk scene as a poet and performance artist, appearing at various Southern California venues such as The Lhasa Club, Anti-Club, X=Art, Al's Bar, Safari Sam's and Club Lingerie. In the mid-1980s, Griffin became directly involved in DIY publishing as a staff member of Shattersheet, and in 1988 he established Rose of Sharon Press with the publication of Sharktalk by Doug Knott. In 1989 Griffin was named Best Performance Poet by Wanda Coleman in the LA Weekly.
In addition to a deep level of involvement in the community through writing, publishing, performing, and hosting poetry events, Griffin extensively collected the publications, artwork, and related ephemera of Los Angeles poets. These materials relate to Venice West, the Los Angeles Beat poetry scene named after the café owned and operated by Stuart Z. Perkoff from 1958-1962, and the Denver, Colorado Beat scene to where many Venice West Beats migrated. He also collected materials related to influential poets such as d.a. levy, Kurt Schwitters, Jack Micheline, Tony Scibella, and Charles Bukowski. With Alan Kaufman, Griffin edited The Outlaw Bible of American Poetry (1999).
In 1985, Griffin and fellow poets Michael Lane Bruner, Doug Knott, and Mike M. Mollett formed The Lost Tribe. From 1985-1988 and in 1992, the group performed poetry in choreographed routines both locally and on tour. In 1989, the group underwent a philosophical shift and transformed, joined by Scott Wannberg (and occasionally Bobbo Staron and Ellyn Maybe), into The Carma Bums, a traveling improvisational performance group. The Carma Bums performed until 2009. From 1995-1996, Griffin and punk musician-poets Iris Berry and Pleasant Gehman formed White Trash Apocalypse, in Gehman's words, "a spoken word tour…treated…like a rock'n'roll tour," which toured the United States and Canada. In 2010, Griffin went on tour with The Poetry Bomb, a decommissioned bomb purchased by Griffin and filled with poetry at readings throughout the country, intending to "foster disagreements…the cornerstone of our democratic system." Since 2007 Griffin has performed with the punk-jazz improvisational group The Lofty Canaanites, composed primarily of members of Saccharine Trust.
Griffin studied film acting and cold reading with Jeremiah Comey and performance technique with Scot Kelman. From 2005 to 2013, Griffin taught film acting and cold reading at the American Film Institute, and since 2012, Griffin has taught film acting and cold reading for Jeremiah Comey. Since 2010, Griffin has served on the curatorial board for Beyond Baroque, and in 2011 Griffin was the first recipient of Beyond Baroque's Distinguished Service Award.
Griffin continues to live and work in Los Angeles. He is married to Lorraine Perrotta, a librarian and veteran member of The L.A. Mudpeople. Griffin has a son, Spencer, from a previous marriage to Sharon Grish.
Scope and Content
The S.A. Griffin collection of underground poetry, Scott Wannberg, and The Carma Bums ranges from circa 1950 to 2015. The collection includes writings by Griffin in manuscript and published form; an extensive collection of books, largely related to the Venice West and Denver Beat poetry scene, as well as other Beat and Meat School poetry; zines and magazines, which are both poetry and punk related and largely published in the greater Los Angeles area; and manuscripts of authors Griffin published or befriended. The collection also includes clippings and ephemera Griffin collected related to Southern California's punk scenes and poetry communities. Correspondence in the collection relates to Griffin's poetry work and involvement in the mail art community. The collection also contains files related to poetry readings and performances given by Griffin's poetry groups such as The Carma Bums which include flyers, road books, and audiovisual recordings. Materials related to Griffin's acting career include materials on the Act Fast 5 strike, scripts, and audiovisual recordings. The collection includes Griffin's art collection, featuring art by Griffin, Tony Scibella, Charles Bukowski, Earl Newman, and many others. Memorabilia in the collection includes American flag remnants from d.a. levy's grave, memorial programs, and t-shirts from bookstores and bands. The collection also includes the papers of Scott Wannberg, which range from circa 1969 to 2014. Bequeathed to Griffin, Wannberg's papers include Wannberg's manuscript writings and book collection, correspondence, memorabilia, and artwork.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
1. Writings by Griffin
2. Writings collected by Griffin
3.Correspondence
4. Performance files
5. Acting career materials
6. Artwork
7. Memorabilia
8. Scott Wannberg papers
Related Material
Collection of Underground, Alternative, and Extremist Literature, 1900-1990 (Collection 50). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
John Fante papers, ca. 1925-2000 (Collection 1832). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Christopher Felver photographs, 1980-2011 (Collection 1759). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Alexandra Garrett papers and records of the Beyond Baroque Foundation, 1965-1991 (Collection 1615). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Judith Hoffberg artists and mail art files (Collection 1763). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Allan H. Kurtzman collection of material on beat writers and artists, circa 1950-1989 (Collection 362). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Lawrence Lipton papers, 1940-1965 (Collection 819). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Philomene Long papers, circa 1974-1993 (Collection 519). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
John Martin papers, 1966-1981 (Collection 1267). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Stuart Z. Perkoff papers, circa 1952-1974 (Collection 1573). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Kenneth Rexroth papers, 1853-1986 (bulk 1950-1975) (Collection 175). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Darby Romeo collection of zines, 1987- (Collection 1746). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Griffin, S. A.; Perrotta, Lorraine M.
- Writings by Griffin, circa 1980-2015 (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 331, Box 332, Box 333)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  Scope and Content
  Writings by Griffin include published and unpublished manuscript writings, including proofs and galleys, monographs, and serials featuring Griffin's writings.
  - Manuscripts (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
    The published and unpublished manuscript writings by Griffin include proofs and galleys and are organized in chronological order.
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - Typescripts, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Scope and Contents
      Materials include typescripts of Griffin's poems and a play.
    - True Blue manuscripts, 1982, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
      The title page reads True Blue: A tale of love colorful and true... For Sharon From Steve. These folders contain an annotated typescript, the original manuscript, a final bound manuscript printed on blue paper, and publisher correspondence concerning this children's book manuscript.
    - "Where Streets Collide - Pigstreet", 1983, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
      Folders contain an early annotated typescript entitled, "City of the Jealous Gods - Pigstreet" and two annotated typescripts for Griffin's poetry/play which was performed during the months of January and February 1984 on Thursday, Friday, and Saturday evenings at the Figtree Theatre in Hollywood located at 6539 Santa Monica Boulevard, Los Angeles, 90038. Performance flyers included with the typescripts publicize the preview as January 12th with words and music of Doug Knott, S.A. Griffin, and Bobbo Staron.
    - S.A. poems, 1984-1992, 1996, 2004, 2009, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      This folder includes typescripts and photocopies of poems such as "Whorehunter," "Suddenly Down," "Walt Whitman's Beard," "Love Came Home Late Last Night and Fell Asleep in Front of the Television," "Legacy to the Poor of L.A.," "The Cat Knows," "A Reason to Live," "carma bums rules of the road/'04," and "The Collage Is Unforgiving."
    - "Long Distance" and other poems, 1984-2013 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
      Typescripts, some of which are annotated, include the following: "The Revolution," "Poetry Is A Drunk Animal Mounting The Moon," "Poetry Is Fucking," "It Was A Good Day," "President of Nothing," "Bukowski To The Curb," "Let The Music Name You," "Hollywood Bus Stop 1979," and "Kill All White People." Folder 12 contains Griffin's speech for the "Tribe Must President" Out of Historical Necessity which he performed with The Lost Tribe.
    - Notes, 1985 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Stream of consciousness style writing and sketches.
    - Poetry, 1985-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Handwritten and typed poems which include "There Is A River," "I Felt You In My Morning Coffee," and "Remember These Words."
    - S.A. Griffin Poetry, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      A collection of poems which include "Pigstreet," "Bad Poetry," "Football And Beer," "Paperwork,"and "The America Poem."
    - Poems, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      This folder contains an annotated version of "Other Side Of The Television."
    - Poetry, 1988-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      Poems include "The Next Bukowski," "On The Work Of Burroughs," and "A Strange Peace (for Misty Mallory)."
    - Poetry Notebooks, circa 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
      Four spiral bound notebooks filled with Griffin's handwritten poetry, notes, and sketches.
    - Group poem, 1992 February 29 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      A twenty-eight page group poem entered and printed on leap day at Bruce Morasch's s.r.o. poetry and beer party at the West Los Angeles Poetry Palace. Contributing writers included S.A. Griffin and Scott Wannberg.
    - "#128" poem, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      A poem written in pencil on a white piece of cardboard.
    - L.A. Riot poem draft, 1992 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Eleven pages of Griffin's handwritten poetic response to the uprising in Los Angeles following the Rodney King verdict.
    - Cannabis Cup journal (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Journal contains writing, art and ephemera from Griffin's trip to Amsterdam with Tony Scibella.
    - Heaven galleys, 1993 April (Box 3, Folder 3)
      One 3.5 inch floppy disk.
      Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
      In addition to galleys for Heaven Is One Long Naked Dance, this folder contains a floppy disk, an original paste-up flyer for the book's release, and a black and white Jeffoto photo of Griffin wearing his Rip Griffin's Truck Travel Centers t-shirt.
    - S.A. Griffin poetry, 1993-2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Poems include "Hate for Breakfast," "Music For Shredding Metal By Candlelight (for Kurt Cobain)," "The Soft Poetic/Easter Hill (for Janice Ugland)," and "(Untitled) Poem For A Sudden Stranger." This folder also contains a floppy disk labeled "S.A. Griffin Poetry: This Has Everything."
    - Burt Lancaster...poem, 1993-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Computer print-out of "Burt Lancaster And The 12 Year Old Bottle of Booze" poem for Rafael RJ Alvarado's birthday. Authors cited for this poem are as follows: S.A. Griffin, Doug Knott, Mike M. Mollett, Lorraine Perrotta, Blakeslee Stevens, and Scott Wannberg.
    - 12 Kisses...galleys, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
      Folder contains 12 Kisses To The Universe For J.W. McCullough galleys and manuscripts of poems included in this chapbook published in memory of J.W. McCullough by Griffin's Rose of Sharon Press.
    - Duckwalking...typescripts, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
      Folders contain five annotated typescripts of Duckwalking Thru The Apocalypse which includes the following poems: "Food Shopping," "A Blessing For The Arts," "A House Divided," and "At The Spanish Drag Queen Place on Santa Monica Blvd."
    - Walt Whitman's...galleys, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Paste-up boards and galleys for Walt Whitman's Beard, a chapbook published by Rose of Sharon Press in celebration of National Poetry Month at the University of Southern California. A final copy of this artifact dedicated to the memory of Allen Ginsberg is included and contributors writers are the following: Laurel Ann Bogen, Millicent Borges, Dennis Cruz, S.A. Griffin, Doug Knott, Jeff McDaniel, Ellyn Maybe, Patricia Wagner, Scott Wannberg, and Pam Ward.
    - (Exploding Text)...galleys, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      (Exploding Text) On the Work of Burroughs was created for the May 10th Tribute to Allen Ginsberg at Beyond Baroque. The exploding text from Ginsberg's piece, "On Burroughs Work" was altered and added to by S.A. Griffin, Mike Bruner, Olly Ruff, David Rhaesa, Derek Beaulieu, Marie Countryman, Michael Stutz, and James Stauffer.
    - Big Belly anthology, circa 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      The cover describes this as a "spontaneous anthology of L.A. and S.F. poets assembled at the attic on the eve of scattering jack micheline's ashes over brown bag farm." Contributors include: S.A. Griffin, Tarin Towers, Alan Kaufman, Rafael FJ Alvarado, Hank Hyena, St. Theresa Stone, Eugene Ostachevsky, Bucky Sinister, Doug Knott, Katie Degentesh, and Kathleen Wood.
    - Wedding vows, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Three pages of vows written by Griffin for the wedding of Rob Zabrecky and Tommy at the Old Griffith Park Zoo, August 8, 1998. Zabrecky was a member of Possum Dixon, a magician and an actor. Griffin met Rob through Pleasant Gehman when they did a gig at the Pik Me Up Cafe around 1992. Griffin tailors the ceremonies to suit the couple even these vows have not fundamentally changed since he performed his first wedding in 1995 for Eric Brown and Tori Williams. According to Griffin, each set of vows is altered with personal questions and other slight additions so that it remains unique. For more information on Griffin's wedding performances please consult the subject files for Universal Life Church and Temple of Man.
    - "The Edge Generation", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      This piece may be located in its published form in Box 15. It was published in (Sic) Vice & Verse, Issue 7, June-July 1999, One Year Anniversary Issue.
    - The Dear Lady...typescripts, 1999, undated, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      This folder contains the following poems: "My Dear Lady Night (for Philomene Long)," "New Year's Party," and "The Vision." These typescripts include Griffin's annotations.
    - Re)verb submission, 2003 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Griffin's submission to Re)verb includes a letter and typescript of his work entitled, "This One (The Bald Headed Mouse)."
    - The Carma Bums...paste-up boards, 2004 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Paste-up boards for The Carma Bums' Armageddon Outta Here! chapbook. This chap was written and produced by The Carma Bums: Doug Knott, Mike Mollett, Mike Bruner, S.A. Griffin, and Scott Wannberg.
    - T's Mile High Parade galleys, 2004 October 20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Folder contains galleys for T's Mile High Parade chapbook published by Black Ace/Temple of Man.
    - Reflections...submission, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Folder contains "Reflections of A Mind Corrupted By A Nightmare Childhood & Congenital Dysfunction" manuscript and correspondence from The Editors of The Atlantic Monthly.
    - Numbskull Sutra galleys, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
      Folders 4 and 5 contain galleys for Numbskull Sutra, a collection of Griffin's poetry edited by John Dorsey and David Smith for Rank Stranger Press. Folder 6 contains a handwritten "Numbskull Sutra (for Mark Hartenbach)" manuscript and a typescript of this piece in addition to the following excerpt from Hartenbach's "land of nod": "i am the numbskull sutra/ to be read then destroyed/ i am the gospel truth/ that will never make it/ through the editing process."
      Folder 5 contains two CD-Rs. One is labeled Numbskull Sutra Text and the other, Numbskull Sutra Cover Images.
    - Black Ace Book 8 galleys, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
      Folder 8: Four CD-Rs
      Black Ace Book 8 is dedicated to Tony Scibella, published by S.A. Griffin for Temple of Man, and edited by John Macker, Marsha Getzler, and S.A. Griffin. The manuscript includes work by Scibella, Todd Moore, Saul White, Jack Micheline, Stuart Z. Perkoff, James Ryan Morris, Philomene Long, John Thomas, Frank T. Rios, Steve Wilson, Ellyn Maybe, Diana di Prima, Ed Ward, and Marcia Ward among others. Folders 8-10 contain art work, digital files, and correspondence concerning this publication.
    - Poems, 2007-2011 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Poems include "Walking the Line," "what it is (for Todd Moore's 70th)," "27 Years in El Lay," and "Rivers (for Langston Hughes)."
    - American Garbage Head script, 2011 June 16 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Griffin wrote and annotated this script based on Confessions of An American Garbage Head by Mark Hartenbach.
    - "Flowers" poem, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
      This one page poem is handwritten in black ink on lined paper.
  - Monographs (Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 331, Box 332)
    The monographs featuring Griffin's writings include the writings of The Lost Tribe, The Carma Bums, and White Trash Apocalypse.
    Books from S.A. Griffin's library that were originally donated with the papers have been individually cataloged in the UCLA Library online catalog. Records for these items may be found by searching the Special Coll/Archive SPAC "SALA" using the Advanced search tab in the Library catalog, or keyword searching "Books from the Library of S.A. Griffin".
  - Serials (Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 333)
    Serials featuring Griffin's writings, which include serials that he published, have been organized alphabetically by title of publication.
    Biography/History